<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "book.dtd">
<book>
	<id>userGuide</id>
	<title>User guide</title>
	<chapter>
		<title>Understanding the model</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The model is very simple. It is based on four notions :
				<ul>
					<li>Collaborators : people who may contribute to the tasks defined
					in the task repository</li>
					<li>Tasks : repository containing all the tasks identified on your
					project</li>
					<li>Durations : possible values or a contribution's duration</li>
					<li>Contributions (see below)</li>
				</ul>
				A contribution is defined by : 
				<ul>
					<li>a contributor (choosen in the collaborator repository)</li>
					<li>a task (choosen in the task repository)</li>
					<li>a duration (choosen in the duration repository)</li>
					<li>a date</li>
				</ul>
				<center>
					<img src="uml-diagram.gif"/>
				</center>
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<id>rules</id>
		<title>Basic rules</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				Activity Manager is based on three basic rules :
				<ol>
					<li>
						A task that has one or more subtasks :
						<ul>
							<li>can not accept any contribution (<italic>which means that when
							you update a collaborator's contributions through the</italic>
							<a href="#contributions" type="book-ref"><italic>contributions tab</italic></a><italic>,
							you can only choose leaf tasks (if you consider that the
							task repository	is a tree)</italic>)
							</li>
							<li>represents an aggregation of its subtasks (<italic>for 
							example, its contributions consumption sum is the result
							of its subtasks contribution consumptions</italic>). For such a
							task, 'Initial fund', 'Initial consumption' and 'Todo' 
							fields are not updatable.
							</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
						A task that is associated to one or more contributions :
						<ul>
							<li>can not admit any subtask (<italic>which means that if you
							try to add a subtask to such a task through the</italic>
							<a href="#tasks" type="book-ref"><italic>tasks tab</italic></a><italic>,
							you will get an error</italic>)
							</li>
							<li>has updatable 'Initial fund', 'Initial consumption' 
							and 'Todo' fields.
							</li>
						</ul>
					</li>
					<li>
						Sister tasks must have different codes (which means that two
						tasks may have the same code, but then, they cannot have
						the same parent task). 
					</li>
				</ol>
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<id>startup</id>
		<title>Starting the application</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				To start the application, double click on the file 
				<code>bin\activitymgr.bat</code>
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="database-tab-small.png" src="database-tab.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>	
	<chapter>
		<id>dbinit</id>
		<title>Database connection and initialization</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				In the database tab, choose one of the three different modes :
				<ul>
					<li>Standalone mode (with an embeded HSQL database)</li>
					<li>MySQL Server mode</li>
					<li>Custom mode (user defined database for skilled users)</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				Standalone mode allows to start using Activity Manager quickly.
				In this mode, an embedded HSQLDB database is used. Just select
				a filename (in which the data will be stored) and click on 'Connect'.
				For the first connection, Activity Manager suggest to initialize
				the database (click Ok in the popup).
				
			</p>
			<p>
				In MySQL server mode, you have to provide the connection settings 
				(database host, database name, user id and password) before clicking
				on 'Connect'. As for standalone mode, Activity Manager suggests
				to initialize the database.
			</p>
			<p>
				In Custom mode, you will have to provide a custom JDBC driver
				(just add the driver jars in the <code>lib</code> directory and
				restart the tool). You may also have to create the database tables
				by yourself (with the default MySQL script as a model for example).
				This mode is only for skilled users. If the	tables are not installed
				when you click on 'Connect', Activity Manager will try to initialize
				it with the MySQL initialization script (which may not be compatible
				with your custom database; <bold>WARNING : this mode may not work
				properly as the tool's SQL requests	may not be compatible with your
				database</bold>).
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Durations repository administration</title>
		<body>
			<p>A duration is a percentage of a day.</p>
			<p>
				Activity Manager has a default duration repository containing 4 values 
				that you can optionnaly install if you want (when you connect for the
				first time to a database or when you reinstall the database) :
				<ul>
					<li>0.25 (=25% of a day)</li>
					<li>0.50 (=50% of a day)</li>
					<li>0.75 (=75% of a day)</li>
					<li>1.00 (=100% of a day=one day)</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				The correspondant tab allows you to create, modify and remove
				durations from the repository.
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="durations-tab-small.png" src="durations-tab.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
			<p>To add a new duration, simply click on the right mouse button and
			choose 'New duration' on the popup menu. A new popup windows displays
			in which you enter the new duration.</p>
			<p>To modify a duration, double click on it and modify it.</p>
			<p>To remove a duration, click on the right mouse button and
			choose 'Remove' on the popup menu after having selected the duration 
			to remove.</p>
			<p>To enable or disable a duration, use the checkbox on the left. A
			disabled duration will be hidden in the contributions tab.</p>
			<p><bold>WARNING: a duration which is used at least by one contribution
			cannot be modified or removed</bold></p>
			<p>To export the window table content, click on the right mous button,
			choose 'Export' and select a destination file.</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Collaborators repository administration</title>
		<body>
			<p>A collaborator is characterized by :
				<ul>
					<li>an identifier : a unique string that identifies the collaborator</li>
					<li>his first name</li>
					<li>his last name</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				The correspondant tab allows you to create, modify and remove
				collaborators from the repository.
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="collaborators-tab-small.png" src="collaborators-tab.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
			<p>To add a new collaborator, simply click on the right mouse button and
			choose 'New collabortor' on the popup menu. A collaborator with default
			attributes is created. Modify these attributes by clicking on it and
			typing the new values.</p>
			<p>To enable or disable a collaborator, use the checkbox on the left. A
			disabled collaborator will be hidden in the contributions tab.</p>
			<p>You can click on the column headers to sort the collaborators.</p>
			<p>The 'List contrib.' menu item opens a popup windows listing all the
			contributions associated to the selected user.</p>
			<p>To export the window table content, click on the right mous button,
			choose 'Export' and select a destination file.</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<id>tasks</id>
		<title>Tasks repository administration</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				A task is characterized by :
				<ul>
					<li>a name</li>
					<li>a code : unique for a given task path</li>
					<li>a budget</li>
					<li>an initially consumed sum : consumption for this task that is
					not traduced with contributions through the 
					<a href="#contributions" type="book-ref">contributions tab</a>.</li>
					<li>a consumed sum : this sum is the result of all the contributions
					that have been created through the 
					<a href="#contributions" type="book-ref">contributions tab</a> plus the initially
					consumed sum.</li>
					<li>a todo sum : represents the amount of work that still has to 
					be done</li>
					<li>a delta sum : a positive value indicates that you are in advance, a negative 
					value indicates that you are late (= 'budget' - 'initially consumed'
					- 'consummed' - 'todo')</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				The correspondant tab allows you to create, modify, remove and move 
				tasks from the repository.
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="tasks-tab-small.png" src="tasks-tab.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
			<p>To add a new task, simply click on the right mouse button and
			choose 'New task' or 'New subtask' on the popup menu. A task with default
			attributes is created. Modify these attributes by clicking on it and
			typing the new values.</p>
			<p>Note :
				<ul>
					<li>The 'Name' and 'Code' columns are always updatable</li>
					<li>The 'Budget', 'Initially consumed' and 'Todo' columns are 
					updatable only for leaf tasks (see <a href="#rules" type="book-ref">Basic rules</a>
					for more details).</li>
					<li>The 'Consumed' and 'Delta' columns are read-only (calculated by
					the application)</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>The top search filter allows you to find a task by its name or its code.</p>
			<p>The 'List contrib.' menu item opens a popup windows listing all the 
			contributions associated to the selected task.</p>
			<p>The 'Export' menu item allows you to generate an EXCEL file containing
			the task tree as it is represented on the screen.</p>
			<p>To export the window table content, click on the right mous button,
			choose 'Export' and select a destination file (<bold>WARNING : only the tasks
			present	on the screen will be exported, not the full tasks repository</bold>).
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<id>contributions</id>
		<title>Contributions management</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				A contribution is characterized by :
				<ul>
					<li>a contributor : the collaborator involved in this contribution</li>
					<li>a date</li>
					<li>a task</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				The correspondant tab allows you to create, modify and remove
				contributions from the repository.
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="contributions-tab-small.png" src="contributions-tab.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
			<p>You can choose the contributor by using the list which is on the left.</p>
			<p>For each day, a contribution sum is calculated and shown in italic. This allows
			to detect quickly any mistake.</p>
			<p>
				To add a new contribution line, simply click on the right mouse button
				and	choose 'New contribution' on the popup menu. A popup will appear in
				order to allow you to choose a task.
				<center>
					<img thumbnail="task-chooser-popup-small.png" src="task-chooser-popup.png"/>
				</center>
			</p>
			<p>When the task has been chosen, a new line appears in the contributions
			tab. Then, you can create a contribution by choosing a duration for one
			day.</p>
			<p>Use the bottom buttons to go to the next or the previous week/month/year.</p>
			<p>To export the window table content, click on the right mous button,
			choose 'Export' and select a destination file.</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Extensible report facility</title>
		<body>
			<p>Activity Manager includes a report engine based on
			<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">Jakarta Apache Velocity</a>.
			This engine generates HTML output from templates files. The distribution
			includes 4 built in templates (located in <code>templates</code> dir):
			<ul>
				<li>
					tasksReport.vm (see 
					<a target="newWin" href="tasksReportSample.html" type="local-ref">sample</a>)
				</li>
				<li>
					tasksByMonthReport.vm (see 
					<a target="newWin" href="tasksByMonthReportSample.html" type="local-ref">sample</a>)
				</li>
				<li>
					taskCollaboratorByMonthReport.vm (see 
					<a target="newWin" href="taskCollaboratorByMonthReportSample.html" type="local-ref">sample</a>)
				</li>
				<li>
					monthCollaboratorActivityByDayReport.vm (see 
					<!-- TODO : Ajuster localisation dépendances -->
					<a target="newWin" href="monthCollaboratorActivityByDayReportSample.html" type="local-ref">sample</a>)
				</li>
			</ul>
			</p>
			<p>The report engine is configured through the 
			<code>cfg\report.properties</code> file. The report to his file to see
			how to configure the report facility.
			</p>
			<p>Once the configuration is ready, use <code>bin\reporting.bat</code>
			to genrate the reports.
			</p>
			<p>Ther is no specific documentation to help to create custom templates.
			Please report to 
			<a target="newWin" href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/docs/vtl-reference-guide.html">Velocity reference guide</a>,
			take a look at the built in templates and consult the 
			<!-- TODO : Ajuster localisation Javadoc -->
			<a target="newWin" href="javadoc/jfb/tools/activitymgr/core/ModelMgr.html" type="local-ref">
			model manager class javadoc</a> to create custom templates.
			Velocity is simple to use. Creating custom templates may be within 
			easy reach.
			</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>XML export/import</title>
		<body>
			<p>There is nothing to say about this feature! Just select an XML
			file and click on export and/or export ! If you have any problem with
			<!-- TODO : Ajuster localisation page contact me! -->
			it, follow this link to <a href="contact" type="book-ref">contact me</a>!</p>
		</body>
	</chapter>

</book>
